to be able to talk to you thank you very
much for inviting me
um I'm going to basically tell the same
story that Anil and Kevin told yesterday
uh but using the language of physics in
the first half and Neuroscience in the
second half and I should apologize for
this because it's going to be
um my basic talk or starting from first
principles My Hope Is that many of the
ideas that I heard you discussing
yesterday
um are fully licensed and endorsed by
this um rather Elemental or basic
approach
um as seen through the lens of a
physicist furthermore the reason that I
or my and my colleagues committed this
kind of explanation is if you understand
the underlying mechanics and the physics
of what's going on it allows you to
simulate things so I'm justifying some
of the technical details in this talk
um on the basis that if you can actually
write down the kinds of processes and
phenomena of Interest then you're now in
a position to simulate and provide proof
of principle and my hope is that at some
point
um the agenda the fascinating and
challenging agenda that your group is um
applying itself to May succumb to this
kind of modeling and proof of principle
but I think that's going to be for you
to decide so this Talk's going to be
breathless because I I have to complete
it within uh 45 minutes and we're going
to cover the statistics of life with a
special focus on Markov blankets and how
they induce an interpretation of
self-organization in terms of inference
and a very basal kind of belief updating
namely Bayesian belief updating and then
we're going to move on to a rehearsal of
exactly the same story but from the
point of view of neurobiology in terms
of predictive coding and how they play
out on neuronal networks and then if we
have time I want to just speak to the
core notion of selfhood
um and argue that that may be intimately
related to agency and then ask where
does agency emerge from the formulation
that I will have established in the
first two bits of the talk
so I'm going to start with a question
posed by spreadinger how can events in
space and time which take place within
the spatial boundary of a living
organism be accounted for by physics and
chemistry and clearly I'm not going to
address that question but what I want to
do is just pick out this notion of a
spatial boundary and note that in order
to talk about anything a particle or a
person or a priest you have to be able
to distinguish or separate or
individuate that thing from everything
else in virtue of it possessing a
boundary and spreading it would be the
first technology that boundary is you
know in on in itself a statistical
object and I'm going to read that
boundary as something called a Markov
blanket so for those of you who know who
don't know what a Markov blanket is
um imagine some Little universe and
these are the states of the universe and
these states influence each other and
these influences are denoted by these
areas or edges
and imagine we take some states say my
States my internal States
the Markov blanket is effectively
um a set of states that constitute the
or constituted by the parents the
children and the parents of the children
as defined by this causal coupling and
in brief the role that the Markov
blanket plays is that it provides all
the information that I would need about
the universe to predict how I am going
to change or evolve next technically
um conditioned upon these states here
the blanket States here the internal
states are conditionally independent of
the external States
and I'm going to make a further move
here I'm going to divide these blanket
States into sensory States and active
states where the sensor States influence
but are not influenced by the internal
States
active States influence but are not
influenced by the external States and I
motivate this particular partition
um in a moment I use the word particular
partition deliberately because effect in
effect we've just described a particle
or something more generally with
particular states that constitute or are
constituted by the blanket States known
as sensory active States and the
internal States and this partition
Universal
um in the sense you can see it wherever
you look so here are two of our favorite
things at the top there's a brain and
the bottom is single cell we can imagine
the internal states of the brain
everything I need to write down to
identify the current state of vibrate
its activity it's connectivity the
internal states of the brain will
influence my autonomic system my active
States my actuators which turn in turn
change the external states that then
couple back to the sensory Space by
sensory epithelia that then influence my
internal States and so the cycle
continues and exactly the same partition
or sparse coupling can be found say in a
single cell with intracellular States
constituting the internal states that
influence say the actin filaments that
support the cell's surface that is
pushed into the external States and the
external milia reciprocates by changing
say cell surface receptors that change
the intracellular space and again
establishing this circular causality
that I read in terms of an action
perception cycle in relation to the
brain so that's the basic setup what I
want to do now is to do a very brief
course in physics and then ask what
would happen if we put the Markov
blanket back into play so I want to
start with the basis of nearly all
physics that we know
um articulated here classically as a
launch van equation or a stochastic
differential equation I use the
descriptions to cast it deliberately
because
um yesterday I noticed in the chat
Dennis was was
asking about fluctuations random
fluctuations are kind of itinerancy that
is characteristic of biotic
self-organization and those fluctuations
are Central to this argument they're
denoted by Omega here and all we're
doing here is just writing down a
universe in which the rate of change of
any states of this universe is
determined by some flow which is a
function of where I am plus these
itinerant or random fluctuations are
just sketched out two states here so
this could be
um an oscillation in uh one cell of my
brain it could be quite heartbeat or it
could be me getting up in the morning
doing my emails having lunch uh watching
television and so on at any temporal
scale the kind of systems that we are
interested in show this characteristic
property that they have characteristic
states which they keep on revisiting you
can describe this um in terms of inland
dynamical systems a pullback attractor
you can articulate this in terms of
physics in terms of non-equilibrium
steady state the key thing is to be
something is to have characteristic
states that I return to or at least the
neighborhood of and thought of like that
we can now read this object as the
probability that you'll find me in any
particular state if you sample me at any
random time
and that's important
it's important because we know a lot
about the maths of the relationship
between the Dynamics the flow the
amplitude of the random fluctuations and
this description of the space system in
terms of its characteristic States or
its pullback attractor
um don't worry about the equations I'll
just pick out what we need to know this
is a very generic equation known as the
master equation in some context the
scrolling a wave equation or the focal
Planck equation most simply just a
description of how this probability
density changes with time as a function
of the amplitude of the random
fluctuations gamma and the flows here
but we've just said it doesn't change
with time because I exist so to use
Kevin's notion of persistence I persist
in time so we know this probability
density doesn't change in time which
affords this solution here known as a
health decomposition may sound very
arbitrary but this is absolutely
fundamental and I repeat underwrites
most of the physics that we know from
classical to Quantum and the the key
thing I want to look at though is that
it describes what's known as a gradient
flow on the log of this probability in
other words in order to counter the
random fluctuations I have to be flowing
towards my artistic States in order to
stop the probability density changing
and that's the key behavior that I want
to pursue for the rest of the talk and
so this point let's put the remark of
banking back in play and write down that
gradient flow in terms of the amplitude
the random fluctuations these things
denote circular or solenoidal flows that
give this kind of itinerancy and life
cycles and oscillations
and it what what the Markov blanket
tells you
is that it is subject to the same law
and it means that the internal States
and the active States will look as if
they're trying to increase the log
probability of in this instance the
sensory part of the Markov blanket and
I'm going to interpret that in terms of
perception and action respectively and
just ask the question
how would I then interpret this quantity
here well we've just said that the
states that I'm most likely to occupy
are those are the characteristic of me
they are literally the states that
constitute my attracting set to which I
am attracting so they are valuable for
me they have meaning for me
um denoted by them here
um so one could read this log
probability just as value and what could
spin off reinforcement learning if
you're an engineer optimal control
theory if you're an economist expected
utility Theory
um if you're a free energy theorist the
negative variational free energy is just
a way of writing down this valued
function
um if I just multiply this by minus one
we have a complementary perspective that
people in information Theory will
recognize so this is now known as this
negative log probability that are now
looking as if I'm trying to minimize is
known as self-information information
ethereum or simply surprising or
surprise it's just a measure of the
implaus ability that I would sense this
given I am me and this is the quantity
that is bounded by the free energy
leading to things like the informatics
principle the principle of minimum
redundancy and indeed the free energy
principle
this is nice because the average of this
thing is known as entropy so the
expected free energy or self-information
is entropy so it'll look as if I'm
trying to resist the second law by
minimizing the dispersion or the entropy
of my sensed States and of course that's
the Holy Grail of self-organization in
physics and synergetics of the kind
described by Hermann haken and indeed if
I was a physiologist it would just be a
statement of homeostasis and I have to
to exist I just have to keep my sensed
physiological States within some viable
um bounds that are existentially
consistent and have meaning for me
because they are characteristic states
that I occupy
the final interpretation which is the
one I want to pursue is that which would
be given by a statistician a
statistician would read this not as the
probability of some states given me but
me as a model of how my states were
generated
this is known as model evidence also
known as the
um the marginal likelihood having
marginalized throughout all the external
states that cause my Sensations and
therefore perception and action will
look as if
we have uh it is trying to accumulate or
increase model evidence and then uh we
can read off things like the Bayesian
brain evidence accumulation and indeed a
predictive uh coding
so I just want to
um
illustrate now and try and demystify
that last interpretation with a worked
example just to work towards something
which I think may be very which may be a
useful mathematical image of a system
that is sort of self-caring and I'll
motivate this using the simulation in
the following way what we've done here
is is simulate a lot of little
macromolecules with strong repulsion and
weak electrochemical attraction and
their very existence is the metric space
means that they're coupling is sparse
and that each molecule cannot see
um molecules a long way away so because
we've written down the Dynamics here we
know the coupling we can go into this
synthetic soup and identify some
internal States on their Markov blanket
in essence what we're doing is we're
asking the question is there a little
particle or thing living in this soup
that is identifiable as something in
virtue of the fact that it has a Markov
blanket and indeed there isn't the
synthetic soup uh here the internal
states are coded in Blue uh um
surrounded by the actor the active
States say the active filaments if this
was a little viral or cell like
structure
um that underlie the sensory of the
surface states that protrude into the
external States in cyan here
so now we have a simulation and then
silico little thing living at
non-equilibrium steady state that we've
identified because it's got its Markov
blanket the question is what does it
mean for it to be self-evidising in the
sense that it has to
on average increase its Bayesian model
evidence or the the evidence for its
models of what's causing its sensory
inputs and the answer is is
it's subtle um simple and I think very
interesting simply because of this
conditional Independence that exists
between the internal States and the
external States it means for any given
internal State there must exist a
probability distribution over the
external States given the sensory States
or the blanket States more generally so
what that means is there's a lawful
relationship a manifold or a function
relation relating my internal states to
the probability distribution over my
external States and if I read that
conditional distribution as a basic
belief what that means is that these
these internal States in some sense hold
or represent beliefs about the external
States and we can actually go in and
just look at the nature of these beliefs
and what I've done here is articulate
them in terms of something called a
synchronization manifold where all I've
done is just plot the uh some mixture of
internal States
um along the x-axis and the probability
distribution or beliefs about the
external States and the actual external
States in terms of their mean on the
y-axis to show this synchronization
manifold here this lawful mapping that
just has to exist because there is this
Markov blanket this separation between
the thing and everything else and in
this example what we're doing is asking
the question can we numerically
demonstrate that the internal States
hold Bayesian beliefs about the
fluctuations and the flow of patterns in
the external States and indeed they do
here are the
um the estimated or the the beliefs that
are held Bayesian beliefs that are held
by the intern States and the actual
external States show that they lie
within the 90 days incredible intervals
and these look very much like what you'd
see in electric physiology if you just
look at fluctuations of the internal
States
um in response to certain events in the
external States when these molecules
leave their little Superman pulled back
in again here
the point I want to make with this
demonstration is not only that there
always exists an interpretation of
self-organized or self-evidising systems
endowed with the Markov blanket in terms
of Elite building beliefs or having a
process that looks as if they are
tracking the states of the world
generating their Sensations
um but more generally this is just a
description which I'm sure a lot of
you'll be very familiar with of self
um of self-organization that can be
described in terms of generalized
synchrony or synchronization of chaos
exactly at the start
um first noted by klogens in terms of
clocks that are suspended from the same
beam or wall will ultimately come to
synchronize and oscillate in tandem in
the synchronous fashion that's all
that's happening here and indeed this
little drawing by uh Huygens illustrates
that from the perspective of the
particular partition into Turtle active
sensory and external states where the
blanket States
constitute the beam that's coupling the
two penduli here so from our point of
view all we're seeing here is uh an
inside out to use anil's phrase view of
a completely symmetrical synchronization
of chaos or generalized synchrony
between two sets of States uh
um I've never said this before what I
will say to you I was just wondering
whether now if we replace the external
states with something else like me we
now have a mathematical image of the
synchrony between
the character as a dyadic interaction
between two people and you can imagine
that's being many people or many cells
an ensemble of similar kinds of things
that are constituted in the uh either
Markov blankets but have some
isomorphism in their form will in
minimizing their joint free energy
necessarily show this kind of
generalized synchrony in this harmony
that can always be read as one particle
or person holding the right kind of
beliefs about another kind of person
having a mutual understanding and
implicitly a mutual predictability a
shared narrative in the sense that all
of this can be described in terms of
increasing the evidence for my models my
narrative my explanation of what's
causing my Sensations because 99 of the
time it is you that is causing my
sensation and vice versa
um so that's the physics part uh just to
be to summarize up the existence of a
particle implies a partition of this
systemic States and states of Any Given
system into internal blanket namely
sensory inactive and external states
that are hidden behind the Markov
blanket from the point of view of the
internal States and because active
States change but are not changed by
external States they reduce or the on
average look as if they are reducing the
energy their blanket States and
effectively this means that action the
active States will appear to maintain
the structural and functional Integrity
of the blanket
um a very simple form or basal form of
self-assembly and one could argue a very
simple form of water paresis
internal States appear to infer the
hidden causes of sensory states by
increasing Bayesian model evidence and
actively influence those causes and in
my world we refer to that as active
infants just to highlight The crucial
role of actively engaging and
establishing and selecting the right
kind of data that is necessary to
establish this kind of shared dynamic or
synchronization
I'm going to end now by um rehearsing
exactly the same story but using
language much more akin to what um the
first half of Kevin stock and uh
um the second half of anil's talk
yesterday so this is the perspective
that a psychologist or a neurobiologist
might bring to the table or on exactly
the same phenomena and this usually
starts with the notion of the brain as a
fantastic organ
generating fantasies or hypotheses
explanations on the inside that then are
put to sensory Impressions to see
whether they are apt to explain what's
going on and if they match that's fine
if they don't then you'll get some kind
of Bayesian belief updating I find this
very nicely demonstrated by this 16th
century
um oil painter Fame for doing still
lives that when viewed from a different
direction and give you a very different
impression oops I caught them the wrong
way around so you're meant to see the
um the the bowl of fruit first
um and then uh after that the the face
um and if you do see a face now the
point being made here is that you made
that face it's something that you had on
the inside in your internal states that
is a good explanation for the sensory
Impressions on your retina or your uh
your your epithelia
um and then this
um notion
um you can find throughout history and
philosophy I'm not a scholar but
um I I find uh beautifully
um summarized by helmhuntz for example
objects are always imagined as being
present in the field of vision as I have
to be there in order to produce the same
impression on the nervous mechanism so
again what it's saying is it has to be
on the inside before or you can explain
that sensory impression almost exactly
the same ideas from people like Richard
Gregory
um the notion of perception of
hypothesis testing ideas used to great
effect by people like Jeffrey Hinton and
Peter Diane in machine learning who
indeed built a helmholtz machine based
upon the work of uh or the Bayesian
inference and the work of people like
Richard Feynman
um articulating that mathematically in
terms of this minimization of free
energy
so from our point of view though let's
just come back to this notion of
Impressions on the nervous mechanism or
sensory Impressions on our Markov
blanket the sensory part of our Markov
blanket so I've cartooned that here in
terms of some sensory shadows and not
sensory Veil and if this Dynamics if
this Bayesian mechanics induced by a
Markov blanket is two then what that
means is I will look as if I am trying
to find expectations for this sensory
impression what caused this particular
Shadow so what would that look like well
we know exactly what it would look like
it has to be written down in this form
um from the physics so my internal
States change in a way that look as if
they are trying to minimize this free
energy form of this surprisal or
self-information here
and it transpires that the functional
form of this can be universally
interpreted as a prediction error so
what does that mean it means my internal
state so manual activity is changing as
a function of my current neural activity
plus a prediction error
um in if you're an engineer you'd
recognize these as the equations behind
predictive coding or kelman filtering
usually separated into a prediction when
I predict the world will do given its
currents my expectations about its
current state and then an update that is
informed by the sensory data that I
sample so what's this free energy
gradient here this prediction era well
imagine that I had this sensory
impression here and I had an expectation
that Bayesian belief that it was caused
by a dog and if I had a generative model
that could generate what I would see if
I was correct I can then generate the
prediction
and compare it to the sensation to form
a predictionary which is simply the
difference and all this fundamental
gradient flow is saying this predictive
coding or common filtering equation is
saying is I'm going to change my mind in
the sense of changing my
um internal space in my neuronal States
until the prediction error has been
eliminated and I've minimize my free
energy and the gradients have been
destroyed
so is that plausible in fact it's very
plausible it speaks to a picture which
we'll see in a second uh where we want
to look at
um I think both Kevin and anneal showed
sort of cartoons of this one can look at
um the brain as a hierarchical
generative model generating predictions
so evaluating the quality of those
predictions by evaluating a prediction
error the free energy gradients and then
revising beliefs doing basic belief
updating on the basis of the mismatch
now notice at no point well I ever know
what's going on out there all I'm doing
is finding a sufficiently good
explanation in terms of that which
minimizes my prediction errors in this
instance there's actually a cat and but
that's nice because what it means is
forget about all physics and just
summarize the existential imperative
that inherits from the physics in terms
of minimizing prediction error and there
are two ways of doing that either change
our minds to make our predictions more
like Sensations
or we can act on the World to solicit
some more Sensations that are closer to
our predictions so we can just realize
up predictions actively by changing the
configuration of our body for example or
in our internal state if we talk about
interceptive inference and autonomic
reflexes or we can engage motor reflexes
or I can look somewhere else until I see
what I expect to see and thereby
minimizing my prediction errors I won't
go through this this is what I would
take people through if they did
Neuroscience in terms of the
hierarchical organization this kind of
scheme the basic message behind this
architecture is that say for example
visual input comes in it's a receipt of
top-down predictions from the visual
part of the brain it elaborates a
prediction error that's then sent
forward to revise my beliefs to provide
better Elemental descriptions but
crucially these expectations are
themselves being predicted in a
hierarchical sense
um with this top-down descending
predictions to produce a prediction
error that then drives the high level
expectations more abstract
representations to provide an account of
what's going on below this is exactly
what Kevin was talking about yesterday
in terms of this layer or level of the
hierarchy looking at informing and being
informed by the level below and so on to
any hierarchical depth required the
particular twist in this graphic though
is that um it incorporates action so
here there's another kind of prediction
error that comes from the muscles in my
eye that I could predict and I could use
a prediction error to infer where my eye
was currently pointing but there's a
much simpler way that I can minimize
these prediction errors I can just
change the stretch of my muscle to match
the predictions of the stretch receptors
and what I'm describing here is it's a
classical reflex arc in uh motor control
if I was doing interceptive inference
this would be an autonomic reflex
basically actively and reflexively
um minimizing prediction errors in
relation to deeply hierarchically
informed predictions that are generated
by my model but I'm trying to maximize
the evidence for
um so that's
um the basic story
um I just want to finish the story
um with saying well actually not quite
um
before I do that let me just illustrate
the kind of active interest and the kind
of sort of Engagement with the world and
one way of establishing a very simple
synchrony with the world that inherits
from the architecture I've just shown
you
um what we did here is basically equip a
synthetic subject with a a generative
model that had Dynamics autonomy at this
kind of itinerancy that was implicitly
referred to yesterday in the form of a
central patent generator and then map
this abstract Dynamic to some point in
extra personal space and we told the
synthetic subject or part of its
generative model was that there was an
invisible point that was moving around
and there was an invisible spring that
was pulling her finger
um towards the moving point so that
means that this synthetic subject is now
expecting to predicting to feel a hand
being moved around and see a hand be
moved around but because she's also has
reflexes then she's going to
automatically fulfill these addictions
of the hand movements and cause the hand
to move thereby fulfilling the visual
predictions and with this very simple
kind of reflexive setup we can simulate
quite realistic biological kinds of
motion and also by simply removing the
proprioceptive or the movement sensing
information we can simulate not just
action but what it would be like to
observe something very similar
performing the same action but just
visually without the proprioceptive
input so that's kind of simulation rests
upon this sort of over architecture that
we get some Sensations and that they
um are used to our Bayesian belief
updating by minimizing this variational
free energy or
foreign
s are then used to
generate action and this rests on the um
the Markov blanket that I showed right
at the beginning of the presentation
what I'm going to do now is make one
very very simple move and take this
sparse coupling that defines this thing
from everything else make it slightly
sparse in a very simple but very
important way I'm going to remove the
influence of my active States on my
internal States
and as soon as I do that then from the
point of view of the internal States my
active States now become vicarious
causes of my sensory States
which means that there now exists an
interpretation of my internal State as
modeling not just the external State as
causing or using a model of the external
states to predict the sensory States but
the external States and the active
States now become causes of my
Sensations so now I have a model
of the causes of my Sensations that
include my own actions and it's this
particular move
um that I'm um suggesting or from the
point of view of simulating these kinds
of uh this kind of self-organization may
be a necessary move to introduce agency
in the sense that uh agents will have
some notion some oils can be described
as having some sense of their own agency
the consequences of their own action
because the um their own action is now
not directly accessible it can only be
observed by the sensory consequences
that therefore have to be modeled and
this takes us into a slightly different
and um I think richer world where you
now have the notion of a model that
incorporates explicitly the consequences
of the agent's action I'm not saying at
this stage there's any awareness or
sentence of that agency but just it is
there that is then used to plan into the
future
um to evaluate the different
consequences of different actions so
that you are now implicitly introducing
the notion of planning and the temporal
depth into the Dynamics that then
provide the predictions of what I'm
actually going to do next I won't go
through this in any detail but just use
it to make the point that the underlying
maths is quite simple and has a telona
me or at least an interpretation in
terms of things that people statistics
machine learning and economics would
recognize immediately in terms of things
like Risk and ambiguity or accuracy in
complexity and intrinsic extrinsic value
and where it turns out that all of these
quantities that underwrite the panning
that ensues from having to have a model
of the consequences of my action are
well established in different kinds of
literature so for example the intrinsic
value
is just
um the quantity used in visual search
known as Bayesian surprise it's also
exactly the same quantity underwrite
something I mentioned earlier which is
the principle of Maximum engineering
information or the minimum redundancy
principle and it is effectively the
thing that drives our curiosity it's the
uh the thing that minimizes expected
Surprise by maximizing Information Gain
and I can sort of strip away various
sources of uncertainty and get back to
expected utility but I really want to
focus in the final slide on
um this epistemic affordance that falls
out and is a necessary consequence of
just having a model of the consequences
of my actions in the future
um that I peed in Taylor degree of
planning and if I would say planning to
where am I going to look next I'm going
to look to the I'm going to make the
next eye movement that resolves the
greatest amount of uncertainty about the
space to Affairs out there because that
has the greatest intrinsic value it has
the greatest intrinsic motivation it has
the greatest epistemic importance it is
Salient for me it has meaning for me in
terms of what I don't know and about the
world beyond my sensorium and you cannot
write this down
um with particular examples and produce
sales maps that do actually describe
quite accurately the empirical behavior
of people choosing where to look next or
indeed you can simulate this in terms of
a little agent this particular agent at
a very simple universe and she was
either in universe that where all her
sensory input was being caused by an
upright face a sideways phase or an
inverted uh face and by carefully
choosing where to look next noting that
she could only sample a very small part
of the visual field with her fovea as
indicated by these um images here in
this movie here she can choose the best
places to look to maximize the space in
surprise to maximize or respond to these
epistemic affordances and resolve her
uncertainty on what is she is looking at
and she's indeed correctly inferring
she's looking at an upright phase all of
that can be much more gracefully
summarized by helmholtz and as follows
each Movement we make by which we alter
the appearance of objects should be
thought of as an experiment designed to
test whether we've understood correctly
the invariant relations of the phenomena
before us that is their existence
indefinite spatial relations and with
that it only remains
um for me to thank those people whose
ideas I've been talking about and of
course to thank you for your attention
thank you very much